Agents can be omnipresent. You can have
an agent that is used on Slack, on maybe
your Google workspace. You can have the
same agent in other tools you're using.
Now, when the agent is going through
maybe processes or workflows or
messages, and it's starting to go
through successful events, what the
agent can do is document that for you
and store that within some form of
skill. Therefore, we actually don't have
the problem of loss of knowledge. Mhm.
If you do this properly, you start to
have like a scribe. What would you say
are the kind of like differences or
benefits
>> [music]
>> of the approach in file system versus
like context that is from a database?
The key benefits of using a file system
is the speed at which they can [music]
build. When you don't have to worry
about infrastructure, components, and
tool selection, you're just using files.
But, that speed comes at a cost. Mhm.
And [music] the cost is
>> [music]
>> Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So, whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
A really quick ask, 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So, if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode. Hello and
welcome to another episode of the AI
Native Dev. My name is Simon Maple, I'm
your host for the show, and joining me
today is Richmond Alake, who is the
director of AI developer experience at
Oracle. Welcome, Richmond. On this
episode, we're going to be talking about
context management and memory
management, and where do you draw the
line between the two? We're also going
to be talking about whether developers
should experiment with their data
storage, and also a wonderful question
about how we differentiate between
onboarding humans and onboarding AI
agents. Richmond, welcome to the
episode. Thank you for having me, Simon.
Oh, it's an absolute pleasure to have
you, Richmond, and you're in London, so
we thought, "Oh, come on, we've got to
we've got to invite you around to the to
the Foot Card Studio." So, Richmond,
let's give a little bit of background to
yourself. Let's talk a little bit about
about, you know, your your career and
things like that. You worked with many
companies such as Nvidia and Neptune AI
in the past, and and you previously
worked for MongoDB before joining
Oracle.
Now, I I'm a
big Java person in my background, so
Oracle I work with a lot on the Java
side and things like that. But, today
you are the director of AI developer
experience at Oracle. Tell us a little
bit about We don't need to say what
Oracle does, although you maybe maybe
let's talk a little bit about what is
happening in Oracle in and around AI,
but tell us a little bit about what an
AI developer experience role looks like.
Yeah, so
again, thanks for having me on, and I'm
we're going to have a very good
conversation. So, yeah, you're right,
I've had a very interesting trajectory
across my career, but one thing is very
important across the different companies
I've worked with or the different
companies I've worked at is I've always
kept the developer up front and center
of everything I do. So, when I worked
with Nvidia, it was as a writer. When I
was speaking to machine learning
engineers and data scientists, and I was
writing about algorithms and all the
good stuff we had around computer vision
and deep learning at the time. And in
MongoDB, I was a developer advocate, so
again, focused on developers. And what
that led me to is to understand what
developer developers really want from
technology, how they want to use
technology and experience technology,
especially within the domain of AI. And
that's led me to be one of the key folks
within Oracle database that help shape
our products and features around
reaching developers. Mm. It's pretty
cool actually that you went from
to Oracle as well, cuz I remember back
in the day, of course, when when kind
of, you know, document style databases
came out, you saw the right big rush to
to to folks like and stuff like
that, but obviously, you know,
Oracle's so present in so many different
organizations. It's a It's a big area.
Now, if we think about one area that
you're you're very familiar with today,
agent memory.
In fact, what do we start by defining a
few things? What What is When we talk
about agent memory and memory management
things like that, what do we actually
mean? Okay. So,
with agent memory, it's actually a term
that describes a bunch of systems and
techniques working together to allow
agents to remember and adapt.
>> Mhm. It's as simply as I can keep it.
But, if we just double-click into the
systems and the techniques, the systems
within agent memory are your embedding
model that does the encoding of
different data objects into numerical
representation that allows you to do
semantic search.
>> [clears throat]
>> Then, you have your database, which
stores all the information and allows
you to retrieve information as well.
Then, you have your LLM, which has a
form of parametric memory, which is
static. It doesn't change except you
fine-tune it. So, these are the systems
and techniques that we're talking about,
such as context management, memory
engineering, all the context engineering
techniques. And And so, when we talk
about the context management, context
engineering, what's the difference, I
guess, between context management and
and memory management? And I guess So,
we have prompt engineering as a as a
role that that people like, "Oh, we need
a prompt engineer for this." Do you feel
like
have you seen and do you feel like
there's space for a context engineer
role or a memory engineer role? So, one
thing about AI in the field is it's
moved so quickly, and people are trying
to understand the space, and for
developers, it's trying to understand
the job to be done.
And because we're moving so quickly, we
tend to
just
latch onto something that we think is
something and then start to define roles
around it. Prompt engineering emerged
probably like 2 years ago, which is
nothing. Yeah. Well, well, it feels like
about two decades
in AI terms, yeah.
>> and prompt engineering was meant to
describe the key job to be done
that developers were doing, which was
actually using a bunch of linguistic
patterns to actually steer the LLMs into
a desired outcome, right? We wanted the
output to have a certain have a certain
representation that will come out in a
certain way and we started in a bunch of
crops and prompt engineering became the
job to be done.
>> Mhm. But, the reasoning capabilities and
the abilities of this large language
models actually improved and that led us
to concentrate more on what we actually
put in rather than the the robustness of
the prompt itself. So, we went into
context engineering, which is actually
thinking up thinking very systematically
about the information you're curating to
pass into the context window because the
context window is limited. So,
to answer your question, are they going
to be context engineers and memory
engineers? I would say yes, but will
they be called memory engineers or
context engineers? It's something we're
yet to see, but memory engineering I can
speak to because it's nothing new. Mhm.
Memory engineering is just a
cross-section between a couple of
disciplines, which includes database
engineers,
search optimization engineers for that
work within database domain, software
engineers and a bit of AI engineering.
Mhm. If you just cross-pollinate some of
the techniques and disciplines within
the roles I mentioned, you're going to
go into memory engineering, which is a
set of engineers that really focus on
optimizing the retrieval pipelines or
the latency of the retrieval pipelines
within agentic systems and that's what
they solely focus on. But, they need to
understand software engineering and
database as well. Absolutely. And And
would you say memory management is a
super-set of context management
generally.
>> It's a very good It's an interesting
debate, right? Which one encapsulates
the other? Is it memory context? So,
look, I I'm very biased, right? Um I see
everything as memory. And that's because
I always look to how human work and use
human analogy to actually describe what
I'm seeing in tech today because I
communicate with both technical and
non-technical people. So, when I use uh
human analogies, folks understand me.
The general populace understands me. So,
memory actually is a good way to bridge
the gap between people's knowledge of
non-technical and technical. So, when I
say memory to my mom or my grandmom,
they understand what I'm talking about.
What if I said context? I'm like, They
don't have the context of it.
>> Yeah, they don't have the context
>> There we go. But, um memory really
brings people into that same
understanding um uh landscape where you
can start to build a plan in it. So,
when I say, "Hey,
we have agents in our phone and they
need to remember." So, every information
you give into an agent, the agent is
That's actually memory.
>> Yeah. So, it starts to allow you to
think about ways you can improve the
the chances of that specific information
being recalled. You start to think about
ways you can optimize your retrieval
pipelines. So, this is where we're
heading towards and that's how I That's
why I see everything as memory, but you
can argue
maybe everything is context.
>> Mhm. It's an interesting way to frame
it. I guess it massively depends on your
on your on your perspective, right?
>> Exactly.
>> In terms of how you look at it. Um one
thing I'd love to chat about. We talked
about We've talked about skills now for
the last gosh, three, four weeks on on
on the podcast. Um I'd love to I'd love
to kind of like hear your thoughts in
terms of, okay, skills. Where Where do
they sit in in relation to context and
and even at Tessel, we have that
question like, "Oh, when we put stuff on
the website, should we should we say
skills and then context? Well, you know,
the the the kind of part overlaps as
well. Where Where does skills sit in?
It's very important to get the naming
right within this phase of Hard to name
it, though. It's very hard, isn't it?
And cuz it moves so quickly, you're
like, "Okay, then. We can't use that
anymore." This month we'll say skills.
>> We'll say skills. Next month [laughter]
we'll say something else. And no one was
saying skills last year, like early last
year, right? So, uh where do we see
skills in this whole thing?
Again, I'm a very simple man. Let me go
back to humans. Um skills are nothing
new. Humans have
the equivalent, and they're called SOPs.
Mhm. Standard operating procedures,
which are documentation that you have
within organizations that define how you
do certain tasks. And the reason why we
have SOPs is because you might have a
certain way of doing things, and let's
say you hire someone else, and you want
to be able to transfer that knowledge to
someone. The best way we saw as humans
to do that was to document it. And
really document it in a structured way
where you define the steps by step um
pro step by step um process you have to
take to achieve a certain outcome.
They're called SOPs.
>> Yeah. And we have organizations today.
Skills are SOPs for agents.
>> Yeah. Right? It's just a way of telling
an agent
there is a task, and I'm going to
give a arbitrary name to the task, then
I'm going to describe the task in in in
a certain uh length, then I'm going to
give you step-by-step instructions and
maybe the locations of tools and scripts
or MCPs that allows you to achieve
>> Mhm. this um the outcome of the that we
want from this task execution. And
that's what skills are.
>> Mhm. So, where do they fall into the
domain? Well, if you come into the world
of agent memory, you're going to realize
that skills are actually a form of
procedural memory, Mhm. right? Humans
have procedural memory in our brain.
There is a part of our brain responsible
for storing and understanding skills
that we have. For example, if you could
do a backflip, where that knowledge
actually stored is something called the
cerebellum in your brain, and that
stores a bunch of procedural knowledge
that you have, the ways you do routines
and tasks.
Skills, and if you look at things from
the agent memory memory perspective,
skills are procedural knowledge for your
agent.
I love the I love the parallels that
you're drawing between humans and agents
here. In fact, yeah, I'll call out our
marketing team here who don't tell don't
tell them I I I like marketing messages
cuz that I'll lose all credibility. But,
one of the things that they kind of like
mentioned was it was it was
effectively saying, if you had a new
person join the team, a human, let's
call them. If you had a human join the
team, you'd have to onboard them.
And one of the things that we're doing
obviously with Context is we are
onboarding onboarding agents. And so,
it's about, you know, humans need
onboarding, agents need that onboarding,
too. You have to provide them with that
context, you have to provide them with
those skills and things like that. It's
exactly the same thing, right? And one
of the things I love about what you kind
of said was
um how organizations already have those
those procedures,
the standard operating procedures. They
already have them written down. If
they're only if they're, you know, Yeah.
if they want consistency across the
organization, they need to explain to
developers, this is the way we we we do
things. And if you want to follow
procedure, this is how you do it.
All you really need to do is take that,
skillify it, if [snorts] that's a word,
and and then provide It is now. It is
now. If we use it enough, it will it
will be in the Oxford English
Dictionary. So, so it's it's it's really
about, you know, wrapping up and to
expect a human to be able to perform the
way that we want them to, especially a
developer, a new developer to to to do
that without giving them that
information,
we'd think are we being stupid trying to
expect a human to do that? Why would we
ever expect an agent to do exactly the
same without providing it that context,
that memory, that skill? Yeah. Um let's
talk a little bit about what it kind of
like leads on to what do agents need to
be successful and I think
a lot of the time we blame agents and
you know
unnecessarily whereby actually we're not
giving the agent that that the level of
context or the level of information it
needs to actually be successful. In the
same way if I just said to a new
developer or developer who's just
joining the team, I need you to do these
things. I didn't give them the
information and then they come back and
they said, "Well, I've done this thing
and it satisfies what you asked." I'd
say, "No, you know, we need to do it
this way. We Where are the tests? This
We need to follow this style guide, etc.
etc." We wouldn't do that to a person.
So, what do we need to provide to an
agent so that it can be successful? So,
we'll start the a very simple answer to
that is
information. Mhm. We need to provide
agent as much information as we can.
Mhm.
Then the second thing the answer to that
the second answer to that question would
be data. Information is data.
And organizations are sitting on top of
tons and tons of data. Mhm.
Then you come into my world, I just told
you you need to give them memory. You
need to give them information of
existing
you need to give them existing memory
that contains information that you have
previously and you need to give them a
robust system that enables them to
actually adapt and continuously evolve
and learn. Mhm. I happen to work in
Oracle. Mhm. And it'll be no surprise
that
pretty much all the Fortune 500
companies or most of them
are using an Oracle database. I heard
you Oracle do some work in data. Oh,
yeah. I heard they did. Yeah. I wasn't
sure if it was a rumor, but yeah.
[laughter]
Well, the thing about the unique
position of where Oracle is is
and and this is very rare for any
company in tech. Oracle has existed for
over four decades.
>> Mhm. And across our four decades, we've
seen
different crucible moments and paradigm
shift. We've seen the internet era, the
cloud transformation, data now in AI,
but
because we are students of change
itself, we understand what we need to do
to evolve and meet the needs of our
customers and developers.
And that's why most of the data is
sitting
in in in most of the data you see in
Fortune 500 companies sitting in Oracle.
So, Oracle understands data.
That means we understand what agents
need to actually be successful, which is
memory. And we understand the robustness
and the techniques we have to build
around the agent itself
to allow it to continuously learn.
A couple of points here cuz I think one
interesting thing, which I think humans
are very good at, where
agents are perhaps not as good at, is as
a human, I
I can kind of understand when I'm being
overwhelmed with data.
I can also understand when I need to
seek data. And when I make a decision as
to, "Ah, do you know what? I can't I I I
may have enough information to just
about
be able to complete this, but I know I'm
not going to be able to complete it well
without more information." Agents on the
other hand,
when you overload them with data, you
see their performance degrade. When they
sometimes get just enough data that they
can possibly form an answer, sometimes
they rush that and jump into the answer
before actually getting all the data
they need. And I guess one of the
wonderful things about like, you know,
Oracle customers is that they will have
so much data. Um how does that I guess
my two questions are, how do you get an
agent to the right data? Um given that
there is so so much. And let's start
with that one. My second one as a
follow-on will be, how do you make sure
that the agent is smarter about getting
enough data So, it's not so so much that
it overwhelms it, but it's not, you
know, so little that it it doesn't have
the the the right information and
capability to actually perform the task
well. So, your first question was how do
we get an agent to the right data? And
so, honestly, your first question, which
is it's a very hard thing to solve,
right? And
as we're talking, a few days ago OpenAI
put out a piece on how they built their
data agents. And one of the techniques
that they they actually mention is they
have a single agent that actually scans
it it works at different levels. So, one
way, and this answers the question, and
one way the agent actually works is
it firstly it scans through all the
tables in the database to understand how
what they have in the schema definition
and how they relate to each other. And
that allows the agent to understand how
data is stored and how it's used. But
then, they have the same agent scan
through the code that is used, the
Python code or Java code that is used to
actually construct these tables and
manage these tables. Now, the agent
understands the thinking that went
behind the generation of these tables or
what sort of data is stored or the
transformation that happened.
So, how do you get an agent to the right
data? It's by giving it will be the
answer to the last question, which was
giving the agent a lot of memory of
what's been happening in your
organization. You have a bunch of
institutional knowledge, you have a
bunch of information, tribal knowledge.
The best thing you can do is have a very
secure agent
go through and traverse through this
information. They have a capacity to
understand. And when it's doing this
traversal of information, it's able to
store this in a system that allows it to
retrieve
information efficiently. So,
this is what I will say. In production,
the data you encounter is has a
heterogeneous nature. So, you have
vector, you have JSON data, you have
unstructured structured
semi-structured data, you have knowledge
graphs and but you just need to really
equip your agents with the capabilities
to work with all of this different
variety of data in terms of storage and
retrieval and allow your agent to be
able to scan through different aspect of
your enterprise data securely. When you
actually do this properly with a very
good robust agent memory system, you
start to understand or you put yourself
on a trajectory of really building a
reliable, believable, and capable agent.
It's not going to be one shot, we're not
going to one shot our way through this.
It's going to be an iterative
experimental process of improving the
agents we have.
>> And securely was a really key word there
as well because obviously there is so
much data. How do you allow the agent
the request, the permissions that a user
should
>> It's such a It's such a huge thing for
us in Oracle because again, we've
existed for over four decades and you
can imagine the the the amount of times
we've seen the nature of privacy change.
And the requirements to actually secure
data change as well. Different
regulations from different governing
bodies on how data should be stored,
retrieved securely as well. And this is
embedded in Oracle. Yeah, it's embedded
in Oracle database. You have all the
usual kind of like role-based access
built in. So, it's about the it's about
the agent.
>> So, when I speak to developers in
AI developers today, I'm going to be
very honest. We
don't security on a list of things we
care about comes in
>> You surprise me. You surprise me.
>> second to last. Second to last. I
thought you were going to say second for
a minute.
>> So, comes in second to last.
>> on. We can't What What's last? Well,
>> [laughter]
>> To be honest, I don't know. Let's not
embarrass the team.
That is last. The thing
The thing is you have to think about And
when I say AI developers, I mean AI
developers within the industry all
across. So, when I speak to AI And you
can see Just look at today, right? Um
The The popular thing we have now is um
uh open claw or or claw bots or whatever
the name is now or or mobot.
>> Yeah. Um
the security
issues with that
>> Yeah. open source framework and that's
all I'm seeing on my timeline.
>> Yeah. Because AI developers of We love
to experiment. We love to get stuff
working. But, one thing I actually see
with Oracle developers is this.
Because Oracle, we take security and
privacy,
we keep it number one.
>> It's the It's third, but Oh, no. It's
number one. Okay.
>> It's number one for Oracle. Security and
data privacy is number one for Oracle.
And when you use an Oracle database, it
means that you can move as fast as you
want and you get to worry less because
we are
Built-in.
>> giving you It's built-in. Security is
built-in. It's developer ready. So, you
know that you have that infrastructure
for security in the Oracle database in
Oracle Cloud, which allows your
developers to just do what they do best.
>> Nice. Just move fast and innovate and
experiment because
So,
>> AI is very experimental in nature. So,
let's talk about that user. Single user.
We'll start with single user and then
we'll jump into kind of multi-user and
team. As a single user, um what what
what do you see as a typical context
that will make a single user more
effective? A single user. So, when you
say a single user, you mean a single
user interacting with an agent or an
agent understanding? Okay.
>> single user interacting with an agent
outside of a team. So, let let's say a
single user interacting with an agent.
What And I'll
speak from the agent perspective.
>> Mhm. So, Go on, let's role-play. You you
be the agent. I'll I'll be the user.
>> So, you'll be the user. Okay, this is
good. So, one thing that agent will
actually need is a form of memory we
refer to as entity memory. Mhm. So, the
agent will need to have a very good
understanding of Simon. And it can get
that in two ways. One, we can front-load
this information of Simon cuz you have
data in in all the tools you're using
and we can just ingest that into the
agent's um memory and it's able to then
create uh a persona view within its
entity memory. That's where we're going
to store it. We'll store it in its
entity Humans have this as well.
>> Um we're going to store it in its entity
memory. But or we can just have
back-and-forth interaction and we begin
to formulate um an understanding of
Simon within the agent's entity memory.
Or we have both where we start with some
information about Simon and we build on
top on top of that. We evolve what we
know about Simon. And this would be
things like uh my preferences, my way of
working, my stack, my facility with
certain languages, libraries I like to
use.
>> Exactly.
>> Uh And it's very important we start to
identify the distinction of these
different type of memories because
we don't need to reinvent the wheel
here. Mhm. Neuroscience has been trying
to do this for decades, right?
Neuroscience have been trying to
understand the human brain and the best
way that they've seen they can
understand it is by really distinctively
identifying what parts of the human
brain is responsible for what.
>> Mhm. So, that way you can actually have
a table within an Oracle database just
for entity memory. Mhm. And in there you
have Simon. You have a row for Simon and
it has all his likes and preference. And
you have different forms of
of data. You can have JSON data, you can
have a embedding representation of your
of your likes and preference. And that
allows us to do semantic search whenever
you ask a query. And all of this
information is how you can start to make
a single agent be useful Mhm. for an end
user because with entity memory
you solve one thing which is the
believability of the agent. How
believable is it that I'm interacting
with an intelligent entity? Mhm. And you
see this in a lot of commercial tools
today. So, if you use
chat GPT, I always get this box that
says do you like this personality? Yeah.
I'm like, no.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah. I'm joking. Do better. Do better.
>> Yeah. But you see that even people on
the frontier of this space are trying to
understand how we be how we start to
make these agents and computational
entities believable. All right? We're
trying to understand the persona and
we're trying to modify this. And this is
entity memory. You know the agents are
being asked the same questions, right?
They're like, do do do you like the
personality of this user? No, I would
like a new user for this. Yeah.
[laughter]
So, so I think from the point of So,
what we've talked a lot about there is
kind of like ways of working, right? So,
it's almost like how effective a user
can be with their agent based on cuz
ultimately the the user is the reviewer
there, right? The user is the person
where they when the agent provides
something the user goes, it works, but I
want it to work like this.
And so, knowing and understanding those
ways of working, the personality, the
how a
person wants to wants to see things done
will allow the agent to provide the user
with
an outcome that the user will be happy
with. I guess there's also very
objective answers where it's like, this
is true or this is false. And that's
like, I guess another style of context
which is potentially a truism like, if
you're going to use this library
the this is the API. I don't you know
and we're talking maybe through
hallucinations or version problems but
it's about giving context to the agent
to make it actually do things
um accurately. Yeah. And so there's
when we think about things that will if
we think about a life cycle of this
context you probably have the first that
we talked about there probably actually
changes a lot less frequently because
the way someone wants to do something
well that's probably more about who they
are and the way they like to work than
an API which may change two months later
and then another week and then another
two weeks and and you get updates that
the agent needs to be aware of. So when
we think about context generally What's
the what do we think about as the life
cycle or the the the longevity of a
piece of context? And when we think
about that what what are the things that
we need in place to keep up with the
changes that are required to keep up
with the
the update the refresh of that context.
I'm going to I'm going to answer your
question but one thing is I'll I'll
answer it by talking about the life
cycle of memory or you can switch out
memory for context. Right? So
life cycle of context this also applies
to the life cycle of memory.
>> Mhm. The first thing when we think about
the life cycle and
now I'll speak from a technical
perspective is we need to ingest data.
Right? So ingest context ingest memory
and we have that in typical most data
science and data analysts will be
familiar with this. You ingest data you
do some bunch of data cleaning um then
you start to do a bunch of encoding.
This is where we start to pass that data
through embedded models and generate
different representation and then we go
into the storage of this data.
And then you store it in a Oracle
database and then we start to think
about how can we retrieve the data? Do
we want to retrieve it using vector
search? Do we want to retrieve it using
normal lexical search or maybe a bit of
both, which we call hybrid search?
But then
this is where you start to see a
difference between traditional data
pipelines is you have to have a way to
forget. Mhm. And that's very important.
When you And this is where it becomes
very crucial to understand why naming is
very important. If you work with
context,
forgetting or suppressing information
doesn't come naturally. But when I speak
to developers and I say if you think
about things from the perspective of
perspective of memory,
you immediately start to
it becomes almost natural to
know that you need to implement a way of
forgetting information. Mhm. And
in that life cycle, you need a way to
suppress information, a way to at least
uh make the way information is being
recalled um be affected by other
information that is within the storage.
Now, there's a paper called generative
agents by some folks in Stanford came
out 2023 or something, where it talks
about ways to forget information or
forget memory. And they have this
weighted score you can add it to the
attributes of each memory unit. But this
is the life cycle here. So, we ingest
the data, encode the data, store the
data, retrieve the data,
forget or remember or reinforce the
remembrance of the data, then we just go
through that cycle again. And there is
an augmentation aspect of it. So, not so
long ago in computer vision or or deep
learning, we have a technique called
data augmentation. So, this is where we
we basically I guess now data is is
plentiful, but in in deep learning
computer vision, we used to have a bunch
of images and the way that we actually
introduced a bunch of diversity into our
data set was to augment the image. So we
rotated the image to let the
convolutional neural network see a
different perspective of
ways that an image could be presented to
it in production. This is called data
augmentation.
We can leverage those techniques in
memory engineering or in agent
engineering today because the
information that you get out of an LLM
can actually be augmented by Eva an LLM
looking at the domain and looking at the
information and and you can actually
prompt an LLM to
put in more information that might be
missing or might be important to include
and then store it again, which will
improve the way that information is
recalled or forgotten. I do this with
Eva MCPs or scripts that I have is where
I have functions or MCPs within
my system resource and I use an LLM to
actually augment the description of the
function
and understand the function itself and
then I use
an embedded model to encode this
information to generate an embedding
representation a much more richer
embedding representation of the scripts
so that I can then do something like
use semantic discovery for some of the
tools I have within my system whenever
I'm working with an LLM. Yeah, really
interesting. And and I think when we
we've talked about single user, yeah,
when we move to multi-user, like the the
the thing that that that that makes this
problem kind of like a little bit
smaller for the single individual is
when there is context that goes out of
date
it's the individual that can kind of
like identify and they can probably fix
it or you know,
prompt things to to to update and fix
the data.
When we get into the multi-team
perspective and you have a team of 10,
20, 30, I hear Oracle just be on a
startup now, isn't it? What was it?
Small small to mid Well, how big is
Oracle these days?
>> It's it's bigger than you can imagine,
but it still operates at the speed of
innovation that you would see at any
startup today.
>> Good answer. Good answer. The
So so when we talk about bigger teams
um
you then have the problem whereby
different people could have actually
different contexts if they're holding
things locally can get stale and stuff
like that. I guess there's the problem
then of discovery and sharing across
teams. What would you say are kind of
like some of the other use cases or
things that we need to be mindful of
when thinking about a multi-team
uh AI using, you know, developer
organization whereby context is
important and context needs to be
shared.
How do we How do we go about that? The
difference between now and the days of
before where you had uh large companies
and you had people that had tribal
knowledge and then when they left, then
the left of the knowledge is this.
Agents
can be omnipresent
in the sense that you can have an agent
that is used on Slack. You can have the
same agent on maybe your Google
workspace. You can have the same agent
in other tools you're using. Now, when
you start to see success when the agent
is going through maybe um processes or
workflows or messages and it's starting
to go through successful events or see
other workers do successful events. What
the agent can do is document that for
you.
>> Mhm. And store that within some form of
skill. Maybe generating new skill.md for
us this specific workflow that wasn't
documented by the person that just did
the successful task.
>> Mhm. Um or you could just put it in some
form of skills
they're just workflow memory
essentially. So, agents are agents today
are omnipresent. They can go through
different systems and understand
different systems and they can see
interactions within a secure
environment. Therefore, we actually
don't have the problem of loss of
knowledge. Mhm. If you do this properly,
you start to have like a scribe that's
following you around always writing down
things you're doing successfully or even
things you're doing not successfully and
then share ways to improve. That's the
difference.
>> I love I love that loop essentially of
constantly trying to optimize that by
maybe even how we react or how the agent
does
finds issues
as as well. Let's go we've talked a
little bit about the database actually.
Let's talk about
>> bit about a little bit about about file
system as well.
>> Yeah. Um because a lot of the time
agents agents love to like see what's on
the file system. Yes. And they and
sometimes even when we say oh can you
use this
MCP server over here if it has something
locally it can sometimes just grab that
and if it's still valid context that
might be okay but
what would you say are the kind of like
differences or benefits of the approach
and file system versus like
you know I guess
context that is from a database? The key
benefit of using a file system that I've
seen with AI developers today
is the speed
at which they can build. Mhm.
When you don't have to worry about
infrastructure components and tool
selection
you don't have to worry about oh what
database should I be using or
um what stack what should I have in my
stack and you're just using files
you remove
the thinking of tool selection. Yeah.
The speed is there.
>> But that speed comes at a cost. Mhm.
And the cost is security. Mhm. Right?
The cost is
what we've been spending over four
decades really solving effectively. And
file system is a good interface for LLMs
and agents in general because
they're trained on a bunch of shell
commands and bash commands and all of
this information on how to read and
write files, right? That's part of their
training data. So, they have this
natural affinity for
working with files that we're taking
advantage of today. But it shouldn't
stop there because who who again, we've
come a long way from the '70s and
I wasn't alive in the '70s and I was
just just
>> alive. Yeah, so maybe um
maybe you remember. I don't know, but
there was a time in the '70s where
there was this phrase from the Unix
philosophy, "Everything is a file." Or
"Everything is a file descriptor." And
whenever I look into the space of
technology, it's it's almost like
Groundhog Day because we
the same things keep repeating. Now
again, in 2026
I'm seeing articles where everyone is
saying every files are all you need. I'm
like, "Yeah, we did that in the '70s."
And I think we've come a long way from
that. We realized that you actually need
um
concurrency, you need acid transaction,
you need security, you need data
privacy. And oh wait, when you start to
actually implement all this in file
systems, you start to realize that
you've just built your own database.
>> on the file system. Yeah. Exactly. Um
so, this is what I tell uh my
developers. Yeah. Awesome.
Don't
experiment
with your tool selection. Mhm. Right?
The same reason why file systems are
very useful in terms of the the natural
affinity with the LLM or how easy it is
to interface with it. What would you say
looking forward now to wrap up I guess?
Where would you say context and memory
management are going it
as models improve because I remember
what was it a couple of years ago when
we were talking about prompt engineering
all the time
and you know
prompt engineering I don't think I've
said prompt engineering as much ever
than I have done today in this last hour
or so but
when we talk about context engineering
so much now context engineering is the
hot topic or memory engineering is is
the hot topic for today to make agents
you know
more accurate friendlier to work with
less frustrating.
What's the future path of this do you
feel as as models get better? Is there
is there a space where actually
we rely on context a lot less or do you
feel like actually there's no way models
can really truly understand what we as
individuals or we as an organization or
team want to do without this data? I
think where the space of context and
memory engineering
you're putting me into that prediction
Yeah. Yeah.
>> Prediction in AI is so bad because
they're usually wrong but
>> We'll have you back we'll have you back
in a year
we'll grill you on what you say whatever
you say next. So this is what I would
say right? Over an Oracle we there's
this principle that we try to operate by
which is
we always try to be six months ahead of
our customers especially within AI.
So everyone's talking about context
engineering. We were talking about that
before.
We've been talking about it for loads of
years like yeah you need data. Okay.
Being six months ahead of our customers
we start to realize that we need you
don't just need
context.
You need a way to ensure that context is
retrieved efficiently.
Right? We want these systems to work in
near real-time or real-time scenarios.
Now, how do we start to make that
happen? How do we let this
agents process data in back in the
background and also work in real-time
simultaneously?
It all comes to infrastructure.
It all comes to scalability.
And that's what we pride ourselves over
at Oracle.
Both Oracle database and Oracle Cloud.
I'll give you
where things are going or where I see
things are going. We spoke about agent
memory.
We spoke about memory engineering.
The way things are going is we're going
to go into
a world where continuous learning is the
norm.
Where you're no longer building a system
where you're thinking, "How do I get the
right context?" You're more thinking,
"How do I get the right context or the
right information out of this agent loop
that I can then pass into my training
loop of the actual model and I could
then replace it maybe 2 weeks down the
line because now I've retrained this
model
and the core
latent memory aspect of it that allows
it to work efficiently has been improved
with the new data that I've just
collected. And we're already seeing
traces of this. For example, a few
months ago, Cursor,
they wrote about how they were taking
all the agent traces that all the traces
that you could that they were collecting
from IDEs and they used that to
fine-tune the embedded model to improve
the performance, right? And that is a
form of continuous learning. So,
where we're going
in the next 6 months is looking for how
we can merge this agent loop with the
training loop efficiently. Yeah. That's
where things will be.
>> That's interesting cuz I guess there's
there's context which is very specific
and will change depending on who's using
it. And there's context which is almost
like that that learning like you say
where it's like actually 99% of people
are doing it like this. This is what
they need.
And I guess it's that piece that can
kind of like always get pushed back into
that into that cycle of learning. And
then it's almost like the customization
style context of hey like the skills
almost right where it's like this is a
specific skill for me and there's other
skills out there for for other teams,
organizations, or individuals. And if
they want to do it other ways, they can
do that.
Um but I love the I love the idea of
that continuous learning.
>> That's that's where it's going. We're
just going to get the agent loop
and the training loop together. Yeah.
Richmond, it's been an absolute
pleasure. Really appreciate you coming
down and
and also actually didn't mention at the
start but you were of course were
uh one of our speakers at AI Native Dev
in New York. And actually for those for
those who are listening, of course we
have the London event coming up soon. I
think it's going to be announced by the
time we we go live. So I'll say it's
June 1st, 2nd in London. And maybe see
you there as well, Rich. Maybe. It'll be
a pleasure. Awesome. Thank you very very
much for for for for for this episode
and really really appreciate everyone
tuning in. So thanks very much and tune
in next time.